A Guide to the Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1797-1865
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1797-1865
Library of Virginia
49 cubic feet (108 boxes).
Wythe County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Chancery Causes, 1797-1865 are digitized, use digital images found on the Chancery Records Index available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
Acquisition Information
These materials came to the Library of Virginia in transfer of court papers from Wythe County in February 2022 under accession number 53538. A small amount of additional material came in August 2022 under accession number 53665
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case; however, the judge is basing the decision on findings compiled and documented by Commissioners. Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history. Chancery causes document the lived experiences of free and enslaved individuals; women; children; people living with physical disabilities or mental health struggles; people living in poverty; defunct institutions and corporate entities; or those that may not have otherwise left traditional written histories.
Types of Courts:
Wythe County was the site of a Superior Court of Chancery that held court in Wythe from 1812 to 1832. The Superior Courts of Chancery were created by an act of the General Assembly passed on 23 January 1802. In order to expedite the hearing of chancery suits, the High Court of Chancery was abolished and the state was divided into three chancery districts with a Superior Court of Chancery for each district. For this reason, these courts were sometimes called "District Courts of Chancery." Suits heard in these courts were typically cases appealed from the local courts. A transcript of the suit from the local court was commonly filed with the appeal. Litigants could by-pass the local courts and file their suits in the chancery district court directly.
From 1802 to 1812, Wythe fell into the Staunton district which consisted of localities found in the western half of the Commonwealth. In 1812, the General Assembly created additional Superior Courts of Chancery which included the Superior Court of Chancery in Wythe. The Wythe district include the counties of: Giles, Grayson, Lee, Montgomery, Russell, Scott, Tazewell, Washington, and Wythe.
Locality History: Wythe County was named for George Wythe, a signer of the Declaration of Independence and chancellor of Virginia in 1789 when Wythe County was formed from Montgomery County. Part of Grayson County was added in 1825.
Scope and Content
Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes,1797-1865, consists of cases concerning issues of equity brought largely by residents of the county and filed in the circuit court. These cases often involve the following actions: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, disputes regarding contracts, debt, divorce, and business disputes. Other less prevalent issues include freedom suits, permissions to sell property, and disputes concerning trespass. Predominant documents found in these chancery causes include bills (documents the plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response to the plaintiff's complaint), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, plats, wills, records involving enslaved individuals, business records or vital statistics.
For this set of causes, debt and contract suits are the most prevalent, and mostly concern disputes stemming from land transfers. Estate disputes are the next most documented cause of action. There are very few other causes of action represented.
Superior Chancery:
A majority of the 1812-1833 Chancery Causes are Superior Chancery cases. These causes while heard in Wythe County (Va.) additionally document the activities of individuals and businesses from Giles, Grayson, Lee, Montgomery, Russell, Scott, Tazewell, and Washington counties. Apart from Wythe County, Washington County is the locality most documented in these records.
Due to the prevalence of Superior Chancery, there are also variations in the causes themselves that may not fit the normal make-up of a chancery cause as there causes throughout this 1812-1833 span that have matters heard in both Superior Court of Chancery and the Superior Court of Law. General this occurred when an issue in chancery was sent by the judge to law side of the court for verdict before a final decree was entered in Chancery.
General Trends:
There is a substantial amount of information concerning enslaved Black men, women, and children. While there are several suits concerning the freedom of enslaved individuals, these cases largely represent the perspective of white enslavers and their disputes involving the sale, hiring, financial responsibilities, and legality of ownership of Black individuals. Specifically, there are many cases concerning estate disputes which over enslaved individuals.
Due to the geographic area represented in these records, many suits document the land struggles is western Virginia and general western migration after the Revolutionary War. Various cases (especially pre-1833) list the Loyal Company as plaintiff. These causes discuss land surveys (in (Virginia, North Carolina, West Virginia, Tennessee, Kentucky, Ohio) conducted when Virginia was a colony, including conflicts with the Indigenous Americans already living on the land, the effects of the French and Indian War on property rights, conflicts with the Ohio Company, and ownership disputes post-American Revolution. In these cases, there is fairly standardized language to describe the history of the land surveys on the part of the Loyal Company.
Additionally on this theme of western migration, many suits include issues of defendants moving beyond the commonwealth to Tennessee, Kentucky, or Ohio, complicating matters for the plaintiffs. Many suits discuss key issues and historical trends surrounding lead and gypsum mining, including: the working and living conditions experienced by both enslaved workers hired out to the mines and workers directly employed by the mining companies, including workplace dangers and long-term health risks; business inheritance issues facing recent immigrants, especially women; and the environmental effects of lead pollution on air quality, water sources, and plants and animals in surrounding areas.
There are multiple pre-1830 suits concerning Almerine Marshall and his estate after dying in the 1811 Richmond Theater fire. Other individuals and family frequently presented are William and James King, King family, Trigg, family, and Heiskell family.
These records also contain a box of "Orphan Chancery" which is processed but not indexed. These records contain parts, often single items, of chancery causes that could not be further identified as belonging to a certain case.
Arrangement
Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.
Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Wythe County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult A Guide to Virgnia County and City Records on Microfilm
Selected Suits of Interest
Causes of Interest are identified by local records archivists during processing and indexing. These causes are generally selected based upon guiding principles of having historical, genealogical or sensational significance; however, determining what is "of interest" is subjective, and the individual perspective and experience of the describing archivist will affect the material identified.
- 1803-007: Andrew Thompson vs. Charles Buster
  Concerns fines collected by Thompson while sheriff of the county, specifically a militia fine against Charles Buster a Captain in the local militia.
- 1805-007: John Towney vs. David Doak, Etc.
  Towney claims he should not have to pay a judgment brought against him by the overseers of the poor on behalf of John King as King agreed to care for the "bastard child" of John Towney at no cost.
- 1806-006: John Claxton, Etc. vs Jesse Evans
  Cause indicates the sometime in the late 1700s a local group of indigenous people [specific tribe or nation is not indicated] captured Bridget Claxton (formerly Bridget Williams), Martin Williams, and their children, allegedly killing Martin and the children. Bridget, then remarried, but seeks the compensation from her late husband's estate.
- 1808-001: Robert Ingledove vs. Almerine Marshall
  Ingledove accuses Marshall of selling him an old and broken carriage and does not believe he should pay the balance of the cost of the carriage. Narrates his family's trip to Winchester, Va., and back, and the number of repairs necessary along the way.
- 1809-014: Barney Gullion vs. Hugh Fulton
  Heard in the superior court of chancery, John Gullion identified by Hugh Fulton as a Tory and supporter of King George III and attributes this and Gullion's belief in a British victory in the delays and issues in the land transfer [see August Co. 1811-103: Heirs of John Gullion vs Hugh Fulton]
- 1810-001: John Thompson Sayers vs. Admr. of James Buchanan
  Concerns debt on bond owed the estate of James Buchanan for services performed by James, enslaved by Buchanan, during Buchanan's time as a guest in the Sayer's family home. Material contains descriptions of Buchanan's treatment of James and the unusual agency afforded to him.
- 1812-002-SC: Peter Rife vs Samuel Davis
  Concerns apprenticeship contract of Samuel Davis to learn trade of House-joiner and mill-right [millwright] and dispute of compensation after breaking his apprenticeship and questionable arbitration.
- 1815-009-SC: Mathew Dickey vs. George Reaves
  In an attempt to satisfy a debt owed to George Reaves, Mathew Dickey claims he mortgaged Edom, Below, Edom, Sal, and Criss, an enslaved family, to Reaves, but that this transfer was not a purchase. Dickey asserts that Reaves was to only maintain Below, Edom, Sal, and Criss, until Dickey could repay the debt. The depositions discuss Below, Edom, Sal, and Criss heavily, as well as the character of a William Sexton.
- 1815-019-SC: Cesar (enslaved) vs. Stephen Sanders, etc
  In this Freedom suit, Cesar [or Caesar] is seeking to secure his freedom after the death of his enslaver, James Campbell Jr., and death of Campbell's wife Mary Campbell. The terms of Campbell's will stipulated that his executors free Cesar upon the death of Mary Campbell should Cesar "in their opinion he has behaved towards her dutifully and with fidelity." Cesar argues he continued to do everything in his power to help Mary Campbell and run the estate efficiently; however, the executors turned to past disagreements between Cesar and Mary Campbell and decades old allegations to keep Cesar enslaved. The depositions primarily discuss the community perception of Cesar, and also reveals the legal counsel James Campbell received in constructing the terms of Cesar's manumission which shows the malicious intentions behind the stipulations. [See also: Legislative Petition of Caesar]
- 1815-022-SC: Jacob Vanhooser vs. Jesse Evans
  Jacob Vanhooser claims legal ownership of Bob, an enslaved man, then in the hands of Jesse Evans. Vanhooser asserts that a group of "lawless bandits" took Bob during the Revolutionary War and therefore Jesse Evans cannot have a legal title. Evans argues that his understanding of events affirms that Bob came into the hands of the "board of officers" comprised of Colonel Lynch, Colonel Preston, and Colonel Wm. Campbell during the war as part of efforts to "distress rebels [loyalists]" in Southwest Virginia. Actions legitimized by the Virginia General Assembly in 1782, therefore providing Evans with a legal title to Bob. Appears the court ruled in favor of Vanhooser as there was no proof the board directed the sale of Bob.
- 1815-024-SC: Mary Hines vs Mathias Hines
  Mary Hines is seeking an addition of dower to lands sold by her son [step-son] so she may have somewhere to live in her old age. Controversy concerns whether Mary was the legal wife of Adam Hines.
- 1815-025-SC: David Pierce vs. Thomas Jackson
  Debt: Concerns the death of Jack, an enslaved man, jointly enslaved by David Pierce and Thomas Jackson. Pierce believes he should not be responsible for the existing debts related to Jack as he asserts the mistreatment of Jackson caused Jack's sickness resulting in his death. Describes Jack's attempts at self-emancipation, his imprisonment in Wythe County jail, and mistreatment of Jackson after securing Jack from jail.
- 1817-010-SC: Andrew Baker, etc vs Douglass Baker
  Debt: The will of Andrew Baker stipulates terms of emancipation for Big Tom, Moses, Jack, Sukey and Sam. Andrew Baker's also notes that he desires apprenticeships to be obtained for his "negro children."
- 1817-013: Trisham Henson vs. David Henson
  Debt: The case concerns money owed to Trisham by his brother David Henson. The brothers immigrated to the United States from Ireland along with Samuel Patterson, a neighbor. Samuel agreed to serve David Henson for three years in exchanged for passage. As David could not come up with the money, with Samuel's approval the contract of servitude transferred to Trisham. Trisham claims that after landing in Newcastle, Delaware, the brothers went their separate ways. However, David ended up selling Samuel's contract as well as linen sent along with the brothers and Trishman believes he is owed portions of the funds and he held the contract for Samuel and maintained joint ownership of the linen.
- 1818-002: Trst. for Wythe County vs John Johnston, Etc.
  Other: Case begins in the Superior Chancery held in Staunton, Va., but is transferred to Wythe district. Francis Smith, Trustee for Wythe County, argues that John Johnston fraudulently sold lots of land in the newly formed town of Evansham [present day Wytheville, Va.]. Case contains information concerning the early history of the town, an 1812 map of the town of Evansham, Va., and provides information on the "academy" [Wytheville Academy].
- 1818-006: Exrs. of William Calfee, Etc. vs EXRS of George Carter, Etc.
  Estate Dispute: Largely concerns the estate of William Calfee and the distribution of his property as well as the people he enslaved. There is controversy in the family concerning the possible destruction of the original will. Some depositions of note include John Carnahan's concerning naturalization, as well as John Rice's which describes the whereabouts of Robert Patterson living within the bounds of the Cherokee Nation.
- 1818-035-SC: Mary Cleghorn vs Valentine Griever
  Contract Suit: Mary Cleghorn claims that Valentine Griever used liquor on numerous occasions to first persuade her husband, Robert Cleghorn, into selling to Griever a tract of land, and for then delaying repayment. Mary Cleghorn even believes the heavy state of intoxication in which Griever frequently enabled Robert Cleghorn to stay in for days contributed to his death. Griever rebukes all claims and instead calls Mary Cleghorn's character into question. The case is eventually dismissed.
- 1819-017: John Foster vs. William Crawford, Etc.
  Debt: John Foster is attempting to secure a maintenance judgment due to his late mother, Isabella Stuart, from Daniel Stuart's estate. Isabella brought a case against Daniel after separating on the grounds that Daniel formed an intimate relationship with Nelly Crawford during their marriage. After securing the judgment against Daniel, John Foster claims he refused to pay the judgment and removed from the state. Due to the increased care needed Isabella required because of her blindness, John Foster seeks to secure the money from Daniel Stuart's estate to recover costs her his mother's care [See also: 1800-016]
- 1819-021-SC: Adam Waterford (free) vs William Byers, Etc.
  Debt: Adam Waterford, a free Black man, asserts that while he was enslaved by James Thompson, he sold a quantity of live pork to William Byers and Anderson Matthews, two white men, operating as Byers and Matthews. Waterford claims he is still owed a balance from this transaction.
- 1819-031-SC: Tobias Smith, Etc. vs Benjamin Hill
  Debt: The cause concerns a judgment obtained against Tobias Smith and Ezekiel Kelley by Benjamin for "trespass, assault and battery, and false imprisonment" in Lee County court. Tobias and Ezekiel claim this judgment was unjust and request an injunction on the judgment as well as a new trail to be held in the "county of Scott, Russell, Washington, or Wythe." Both sides assert the other was the true agitator and fraudulent party in this act of assault.
- 1819-041-SC: Anthony Owens vs. Henley Chapman
  Other: Anthony Owens is seeking a new trial to be held in the Superior Court of Law in the county of Wythe. Owens claims that the commonwealth prosecution against him was flawed. The jury convicted Owens of suffering gambling, a game of "hustle cap", on his property while Owens argues he was not present and tried to break-up the game. Owens further claims that various errors in the proceedings resulted in the guilty verdict and the judgment for one hundred and twenty dollars. The judge rules that the Superior Court of Chancery for the Wythe District does not have jurisdiction in the matter and the case should be moved to the Superior Court of Chancery to be held in Richmond.
- 1820-003-SC: Samuel Jones vs Henry Kinder
  Debt: Samuel Jones argues that the judgement against him brought by Henry Kinder is not lawful and that Samuel was not able to defend himself in court. The dispute at the heart of the cause concerns an fight which took place between Samuel and Henry regarding a plank removed from Henry's property by a group of men enslaved by Samuel, to be used by the local blacksmith to fix a wagon for Samuel. The fight was allegedly quite violent, resulting in Henry Kinder being injured. Henry then sought a judgement for damages as a result of these injuries. Much of cause tries to determine who is at fault for the fight. Samuel's bill is ultimately dismissed.
- 1820-009-SC: Daniel Horton vs John Griffitts
  Debt: Daniel Hortons states that he bought a "mulatto boy" [unnamed] from William Griffitts for $600; however, not long after the young man was stolen. After this, Daniel learned and believed to be true, that the young enslaved man, was actually free and that William or his son John Griffitts stole the young man from his home in Grayson County, and then stole him from Daniel. After reaching an agreement for repayment, John Griffitts then took the young enslaved man an proceeded to try and take him south to sell into slavery. While Daniel managed to intervene and collect John Griffitts and the young man, sending John Griffits to the penitentiary, Daniel is seeking to have remaining debts repaid, through the sale of John's lands. The suit was dismissed by Daniel for unknown reasons.
- 1822-019: Catherine Wolf vs John Wolf, Etc., 1822-31: Adam Wolfe ETC vs Henry Wolfe, Etc.
  These two suits deal with issues concerning proper conveyance and distribution of John Wolfe's estate. There are various issues concerning the validity of the transfers in property as the depositions show there were questions concerning John Wolfe's mental health attributed to his participation in the murder of a man in Berkley County West Virginia, resulting in his frequent intoxication, abusive behavior, and his death by suicide.
- 1822-024-SC: Andrew Datton (free) vs William Irvine
  Andrew Datton, a free Black man, complains that he purchased Dinah, an enslaved woman, from William Irvine who has not conveyed a title to him even after the agreed payments.
- 1822-033-SC: Alexander Smyth vs George Wampler
  Other: Alexander Smyth complains that George Wampler, in his capacity as tavern owner, is permitting waggoners to park their wagons in front of Smyth's residence obstructing both the street and barricading him from freely moving in and out of his residence. Smyth further complains of the noise, smells, and general annoyance cause by the presence of so many waggoners with their "well fed horses." The cases is dismissed on the grounds the Wampler will prevent future waggoners from parking their wagons with 60 feet from the front of Smyth's residence.
- 1822-034-SC: Michael Swindle vs Lewis Toncray
  Contract Suit: The suit largely concerns "Jerry" or Jeremiah, a Black man enslaved originally by Michael Swindle, a white man. Swindle complains he sold Jerry to Lewis Toncray, a white man, in exchange for Toncray paying the debts owned by Swindle and releasing him from jail, but with the understanding that Jerry would be returned after Swindle repaid Toncray. Depositions contain discussions of local hiring practices, apprenticeships, skilled enslaved men working as carpenters, and Jerry's skills and general work.
- 1823-031-SC: Joseph Trigg and wife, Etc. vs Nancy Findlay, Etc.
  Estate suit: While a typical matter of estate division, there is substantial discussion about the naturalization statuses of members of the King family as immigrants from Ireland.
- 1825-003-SC: Archibald Hazlerig vs John Jackson
  Debt: Concerns a matter of debt John Jackson owed to Archibald Hazlerig, which is complicated by Hazlerig originally ordering the payment be assigned to Nancy, an enslaved woman, but then claims to cancel the order so is still due the payment from John Jackson.
- 1825-013-SC: John Irons vs John Thompson, Etc.
  Contract Suit: John Irons, a white man, claims he is owed compensation from John and Richard Thompson after selling him Patsey, an enslaved Black woman, who shortly after the transaction died of consumption. The depositions discuss Patsey's life in great detail and John Iron's treatment of enslaved individuals. The case has issues heard in the court of Superior Law.
- 1828-010-SC: Jenny (enslaved) vs Charles Talbert, Etc.
  Freedom Suit: Jenny, an enslaved woman, claims that she was emancipated by Basil Talbert after she bore enough children for each of Talbert's child. After her emancipation, Jenny attests she had additional children, all living as free people, until one of Basil Talbert's children, Charles Talbert, re-enslaved Jenny and her children claiming his father had signed a deed of gift naming Charles as Jenny's enslaver. The judge decrees that Jenny is in fact a free person as well as her children, Lernzo, Sally, and Nancy.
- 1828-015-SC: James Albert vs Andrew McHenry, Etc.
  Debt Suit: concerns repairs and construction done to the Scott County jail
- 1828-019-SC: Alexander Smyth vs Daniel Sheffey, Etc.
  Contract suit: Alexnader Smyth claims there is issue in the deed of trust secured by himself and others including Daniel Sheffey, Peter Mayo, and Benjamin Estill as all these deeds are conflicting claims on property of Benjamin Cawood. Much of the Causes concerns the commonwealth case again Benjamin Cawood for the alleged murder of his wife, and the various payments and claims of attorneys involved in the case.
- 1829-020: Molly (enslaved) vs. Admr. Of George Hancock
  Freedom Suit: Molly claiming (on behalf of herself and her children) freedom because she, her mother, and brother had been freed by Alexander Baine in 1792.